Guide to the Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection
1816-1980
YCAL MSS 446
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.02
(31 boxes)
The Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection contains single letters and small groups of letters acquired by the Beinecke Library from various sources and at various times, previously represented in the Beinecke Manuscripts Card Catalog. Letters sometimes include enclosures such as manuscript drafts and clippings. Folders frequently contain additional provenance, descriptive, or other information not reflected in this list.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Collection of American Literature
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as noted in the finding aid and on folders.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Yale Collection of American Literature Manuscript Miscellany (YCAL MSS MISC) and Yale University Press Records. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection contains single letters and small groups of letters acquired by the Beinecke Library from various sources and at various times, previously represented in the Beinecke Manuscripts Card Catalog. Letters sometimes include enclosures such as manuscript drafts and clippings. Folders frequently contain additional provenance, descriptive, or other information not reflected in this list.
Arrangement
The files are arranged alphabetically by name main entry, which usually is the author of the piece. In a few cases, however, the material is filed under the name of the person who is the subject or recipient of the letter(s). Cross references from older forms of names used as main entries in the card catalog have been included in this online list, as necessary. Two unidentified items are filed at the beginning of the collection.
American literature; American poetry; Authors, American; Poets, American; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Collection of American Literature
- Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1 letter to Miss Alger, 1882 February 12
  - 1 envelope to A. Hart Esquire, postmarked New York, 1914 January
- "A"
  - ABBEY, HENRY, 1842-1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter to Edmund Clarence Stedman in the third person, n.p., undated
      Scope and Contents
      Concerning C. L. Moore, 2 pages
      Removed from: Charles Leonard Moore's Poems, antique and modern, Philadelphia, 1883 (Za.M779.883p)
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Kingston, N. Y., 1889, 1904
      6 pages
      From: Stedman Library, given anonymously
  - ABBOTT, JACOB, 1803-1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS to Mrs. Downs, New York, N. Y., 1857 October 20
      2.5 pages
  - ADAMS, FRANKLIN P. (FRANKLIN PIERCE), 1881-1960, 2 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - ALS in verse to E. F. [Elliot Flower], Chicago, 1900 December 19
      1 leaf
      Signed with initials: F. P. A. Gift of Mrs. Elliot Flower and Dorothy Flower Livingston, 1933 December.
    - Noah Webster: typewritten ms poem with autograph corrections
      3 leaves
      Gift of Mr. Adams
  - ADAMS, HENRY, 1838-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS to Mrs. Bancel LaFarge, [Washington], 1904 November 30
      8 pages with addressed envelope
      Gift of Mrs. LaFarge, July 1939
    - ANS to the editor of the "International Review" [John McD. Leavitt], [Boston], 1877 March 10
      2 pages
      Gift of H. B. Barnes and members of his family, 1940
    - ALS to Lawrence Mason, Washington, D. C., 1915 April
      7 pages with envelope
      Gift of Francis H. Bangs, December 1947
  - ADAMS, MARY M. (MARY MATHEWS), 1840-1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1 leaf, 1895 October 29
  - ADAMS, SAMUEL HOPKINS, 1871-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 2 TLS to the Librarian, Yale University, Auburn, N. Y., 1929 December 13 ,21
      An inquiry concerning letters of Daniel Webster
      With 2 TL (carbons) to Mr. Adams from the Reference Librarian, 2 pages, 1929 December 20 and 26
  - ADAMS, WILLIAM T. (WILLIAM TAYLOR), 1822-1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    (aka Oliver Optic)
    - ALS enclosing one page of ms of his "Rich and Humble," Dorchester, Mass., 1885 September 14
      Gift of James H. Penniman, 3 May 1921
      Transferred from RBR November 1950
    - ALS to D. A. Cushing, Harrison Square, Mass., 1867 February 4
  - ADE, GEORGE, 1866-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - TLS to the Rev. Kenneth W(alter) Cameron, Brook, Indiana, 1939 September 21
      1 page
      With envelope
  - ADLER, ELMER, 1884-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 23 TLS and NS to Maurice Louis Firuski [about the publication of Nobodaddy, by Archibald MacLeish], New York City and Paris, 1926-1928
      One ANS written on picture postal-card
      Plain funds, June 1944
  - AIKEN, CONRAD, 1889-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - TLS to Gerrit P. Judd, 17 Elwood St., Charlestown, Mass., 1937 February 11
    - 1 page [with envelope]
      Gift of Gerrit P. Judd, April 1938
    - TLS to [Will S.] Monroe, Cambridge, Mass., 1929 March 7
      Removed from: his Comprehensive Anthology of American Poetry, N. Y., [1929], call no. Is55.t929, copy 2
      Gift of Charles E. Tuttle, Jr., October 1940
    - TLS to Pauline Frances Stephens, Rye, Sussex, 1935 November 2
      Plain funds, May 1941
  - ALBEE, HELEN RICKEY, 1864- (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Pequaket, N. H., 1902 November 25
      4 pages
  - ALBEE, JOHN, 1833-1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS to Mrs. V. Botta, New York, N. Y., 1885 January 20
      Removed from: Za copy of his Poems...N. Y., 1883
      Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, 1882 March 4, September
      2 pages each
      Removed from: Za copies of his Poems...N. Y., 1883
      Anonymous gift, 1912
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Boston and New York, N. Y., 1883, undated.
  - ALCOTT, AMOS BRONSON, 1799-1888, 2 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - ALS to "Dear Friend," Concord, Mass., 1882 August 22
      Gift of J. T. Babb, 1959
    - ALS to Edward L. Gaylord, Concord, Mass., 1879 May 9
      Written on a printed advertisement for the Concord Summer School
    - ALS to an unknown correspondent, Concord, 1877 February 12
      Removed from: Za copy of his Table Talk, Boston, 1877
  - ALCOTT, LOUISA MAY, 1832-1888, 2 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - ALS to Julia Lippmann, Concord, December 11
      4 pages with envelope
      Gift of James H. Penniman, 1924 July 27
    - ALS to Mr. Niles, n.p. [Concord], undated [1868]
      3 pages
    - One page of corrections, in her hand, for the printing of an unidentified story
    - Single page, with her name at the head, and below the names of characters in Little Women. Dated August[ust] 28 at the bottom of the page
    - ALS to Mrs. Stearnes [?], concerning her niece Louisa May Nieriker, and the deaths of her mother Abigail (May) Alcott and sister May (Alcott) Nieriker, [Concord, Mass.], 1881 February 21
      Purchased January. 1958 from King V. Hostick: funds given by Norman V. Donaldson in memory of Stanley T. Williams; Alvord Fund
  - ALDEN, HENRY MILLS, 1836-1919, 2 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - ANS to Mrs. [Martha J.] Lamb, New York, N. Y., 1875 November 17
      Removed from: Za copy of William L. Alden's Domestic Explosives, N. Y., 1878
    - [The Best Short Poem in English], Typescript (original), signed. On the impossibility of choosing a single poem as best
      Probably sent to Geo. Leon Varney, ca. 1909
  - ALDEN, ISABELLA MACDONALD, 1841-1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - APCS to Mrs. J. A. [May (Shelton)] Kirby, Greensburg, Ind., [1876] October 31
      Concerning her Four girls at Chautauqua
      Signed: Mrs. G. R. Alden
  - ALGER, HORATIO, 1832-1899, 2 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - ALS to William [Rounseville Alger], 26 W. 34th St., Monday morning, [1874]
      2 pages (1 leaf)
      Aldis Collection of autographs
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, 133 East 46th St., [New York], 1875 November 29
      3 pages (1 leaf)
      Removed from: Za copy of his Grandfather Baldwin's Thanksgiving ...Boston, [c1875]
    - ALS to Mr. Elderkin, South Natick, Mass., 1884 August 2
      With typed copy Philip D. Sang, 1955
  - ALGER, WILLIAM ROUNSEVILLE, 1822-1905 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to E. C. Stedman, Boston, 1889 December 28
      Removed from: Za copy of his The poetry of the Orient...Boston, 1865
    - ALS to E. C. Stedman, New York, 1895 April 24
      Removed from: Za copy of his The school of life...Boston, 1888
  - ALLEN, ELIZABETH ANN CHASE AKERS, 1832-1911 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Advice. Autograph copy of 6 lines from her "Advice" beginning "For weariness comes of winning"..., 1896 February
      Removed from: Za copy of her The silver bridge...Boston and N. Y., 1886
    - The Chadwick Elms. Autograph copy
      Removed from: Za copy of her Poems...Boston, 1866
  - ALLEN, ETHAN, 1832-1911 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - ALS to John I. Dalglish, New York, N. Y., 1895 November 6
      Removed from: a copy of his Washington or the Revolution, N.Y., 1895 Gift of Mrs. W. S. Lewis, December 1939
  - ALLEN, JAMES LANE, 1849-1925, 2 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - ALS to Miss Jessamine Florence Dyer, New York, N. Y., 1913 June 11
      Gift of Miss Jessamine Florence Dyer, August 1938
    - 2 ANS to Elizabeth Johnson. New York, N. Y., [1914]-1915
      Removed from: Za copy of his The Last Christmas Tree, Portland, 1914
      Alvord Fund, May 1946
  - ALLIS, MARGUERITE, 1887-1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - TLS to Richard S. Kirby, Old Lyme, 1947 August 15
      With carbon copy of Prof. Kirby's letter to her, 7 August 1947
      Gift of R. S. Kirby, October 1947
    - 2 TLS to [Richard Shelton] Kirby, Branford, Conn., 1948 September, November
      2 leaves and 3 leaves
      Gift of Raymond Sheldon Kirby, 1949
  - ALLSTON, WASHINGTON, 1779-1843, 2 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - AL to Rufus Wilmot Griswold, including quotation from the "Spanish maid." Cambridge Port, undated
      Removed from: Za copy of his Lectures on art...N. Y., 1850
    - ALS to Robert Rogers, Cambridge Port, 1832 March 8
      Removed from: Za copy of his Monaldi...Boston, 1841
    - AL to the Hon. Josiah Quincy, [n.p.], December 26
      In the third person with address leaf
      Removed from: extra-illustrated Pierre Irving's Life and Letters of Washington Irving (New York, 1862-64)
      Gift of Dr. Fred T. Murphy, 1957
  - ALTSCHUL, FRANK, 1887-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Let No Wave Engulf Us: TMS
      37 pages
      With corrections in the author's hand, and with his signature at end of final page
      Gift of Frank Altschul, May 1941
  - AMES, MRS. MARY (CLEMMER), 1839-1884
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: CLEMMER, MARY, 1839-1884
  - ANDERSON, MABELLE (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - America, A Masque: carbon copy with MS corrections, Cleveland, 1917
      19 numbered l.
      Gift of J. R. Crawford, 1922
  - ANDERSON, SHERWOOD, 1876-1941, 4 (Box 2, Folder 34-37)
    - ANS to Jack R. Crawford, New York, N. Y., Saturday, undated
      Gift of J. R. Crawford (Libr. Assoc.), May 1939
    - 3 ALS to Jack R. Crawford, New York, 1922, undated
      Gift of Professor Crawford, February 1951
    - ALS and TLS to John (Waldhorn) Gassner, [n.p.], [1933]
      Concerning his own dramatization of his Winesburg, Ohio. With a TLS from Mr. Gassner to the Librarian, 9 October 1956, concerning these letters
    - 2 ALS to Fred Robbins, [n.p.], undated
      With a TLS from Eleanor (Copenhaver) Anderson to Mr. (Fred) Robbins, Marion, Va., 10 September 1943, concerning the letters Philip D. Sang, 1955
    - TL (carbon) to Mr. Barton, Chicago, Ill., 1918 June 25
      Suggesting that Sherwood Anderson be fired. Written on stationery of Critchfield and Co. Philip D. Sang, 1955
    - ALS to Mrs. A. J. Smith, [n. p.], undated
      Gift of Ralph D. Allan, 1951
  - ANDREWS, MARY RAYMOND SHIPMAN, d. 1936 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - ALS to Miss Day, "Monday the 19th," Onondaga, N. Y., agreeing to autograph and send a copy of her Perfect Tribute, undated
      Gift of Mr. J. T. Babb, 1959
  - ANSPACHER, LOUIS KAUFMAN, 1878-1947 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - The Sacrament. July 14th. Typescript (carbon), signed
      "Used by the National Committee on the occasion of the American celebration of Bastille Day, 1917"
      Gift of Walter L. Pforzheimer, December 19, 1959
    - Comrades of the Mist. Typescript (carbon), signed
    - The Song of the Shipbuilder. Typescript (carbon), signed
  - ANTHONY, KATHARINE SUSAN, 1877-1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - TLS to Richard I. Anthony, New York, 1955 March 12
  - ANTHONY, SUSAN B. (SUSAN BROWNELL), 1820-1906 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Autograph sentiment signed. Rochester, N. Y., 1898 January 1
      Gift of James T. Babb, 1962
    - Printed form signed, Warren, Ohio, 1899 June 13
      Sight draft, made out to Harriet Taylor Upton, signed by Miss Anthony as president of the National American Woman Suffrage Association
  - ANTHONY, THEODORE VAN WYCK (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - TLS to George H. Nettleton, Newburgh, N. Y., 1933 April 11
      Removed from: his Chiefly Hellenic reveries, [Newburgh, N.Y.], 1933. Is55.t1.An86
      Gift of George H. Nettleton, 1945
  - APPLETON, THOMAS GOLD, 1812-1884, 2 (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
    - ALS to "My dear Sir", April 26
      Removed from: Za copy of his Life and letters...N. Y., 1885
    - LS to an unidentified correspondent, Boston, Mass., 1878 March 4
      The body of the letter is in the hand of an amanuensis
      Gift of Robert F. Metzdorf, 1958
  - ARTHUR, T. S. (TIMOTHY SHAY), 1809-1885 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - 2 ALS to Robert Bonner, Philadelphia, Pa., 1860, 1862
  - ARVIN, NEWTON, 1900-1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - TLS to the Librarian, Yale University, Saratoga Springs, N. Y. An inquiry concerning Edward Rowland Sill, 1930 July15
      From Ref. Dept. files
  - ASH, SARAH LEEDS (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - In Solitude: typewritten MS of poem
      Removed from: her Just little things, [Phila.], 1941
    - The Summer Now: typewritten MS of poem
    - Vagabond: typewritten MS of poem
  - ATHERTON, GERTRUDE FRANKLIN HORN, 1857-1948, 2 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
    - ANS to "My dear friend," "Sunday[?]," [n. p.] / "Hotel Albert", undated
    - ALS to Stone and Kimball (publishers, Chicago), Yonkers, N. Y., [1894] April 15
    - ALS to Florence Hayward, London, Eng., [1898 May 17]
  - ATLEE, EDWIN AUGUSTUS, 1776-1852 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - ALS to Dr. Jo[hann] Fr[iedrich] Im[manuel] Tafel, Philadelphia, Pa., 1835 May 19
      In Latin
  - AUSTIN, JANE G. (JANE GOODWIN), 1831-1894 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - ALS to J(ames) R(ipley) Osgood, Holden, Mass., 1882 July26
      2 leaves
  - AUSTRIAN, JOSEPH E., 1869- (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "Ramsch" or, The letters of a self-made embroidery merchant to his partners, [New York] c1909
      7 v. in 1.
      Typewritten ms on business paper with heading: Spineless, Weakknees and Co. Manufacturers and importers of embroideries and datings... No title-page; title printed at bottom of page 1 of letters no. 3-7
- "B"
  - BACHELLER, IRVING, 1859-1950, 2 (Box 2, Folder 53-54)
    - ALS to Melville Phillips, Washington, D. C., 1897 January 21
      Removed from: Za copy of his Eben Holden
    - ALS to Dr. Peck, Sound Beach, Conn., 1904 July 22
      Gift of James H. Penniman
    - ALS to Mrs. Holloway, [n.p.], undated
  - BALLOU, MATURIN MURRAY, 1820-1895 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - [Ballads]. AMS, dated, Boston, 1882 June 14
      A short essay
      Purchased August. 1967 Barney Fund
  - BANCROFT, GEORGE, 1800-1891, 3 (Box 2, Folder 56-58)
    - ALS to C. Campbell, Boston, 1840 November 20
      Removed from: Za copy of his History of the colonization of the United States...v. 1, Boston, 1841
    - ALS to Henry Reed, New York, 1852 October 17
      Removed from: Za copy of his Poems...Cambridge, 1823
    - ALS, New York, 1862 March 15
      Removed from: Za copy of his Memorial address...on Abraham Lincoln...Washington, 1866
    - ANS, N. Y., 1856 April 4
      Removed from: Za copy of his Literary and historical miscellanies...N. Y., 1855
    - ANS to [Nathaniel Parker?] Willis, Washington, 1846 May 16
      Gift of Mr. Knollenberg, January 1946
    - ALS to an unidentified correspondent, New York, N. Y., 1858 May 21
      Gift of the Rev. Kenneth W. Cameron, 1957
    - History of the United States [volume 3, Chapt. XXIV, end]. Autograph ms
      Passage concerning George Washington; signed and dated 1844 February 8, Boston, Mass. Removed from: extra-illustrated Pierre Irving's Life and Letters of Washington Irving (New York, 1862-64)
  - BARBE, WAITMAN, 1864-1925 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Parkersburg, W. Va., 1892 February 7, 21
  - BARBOUR, L. G. (LEWIS GREEN), 1829-1907 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Richmond, Ky., 1894 January 1
      1 leaf with envelope
  - BARNARD, FREDERICK A. P. (FREDERICK AUGUSTUS PORTER), 1809-1889 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Two ANS to Amelia M. Daggett, Columbia College, [New York, N. Y.], 1877 May 22, 24
      1 page and 2 pages with envelopes
      From the Estate of Mrs. George St. John Sheffield, June 1937
  - BARNARD, GEORGE GREY, 1863-1938 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - ALS to James Gibbons Huneker, New York, N. Y., 1908 November 20
      Plain funds, Sept. 1941
  - BARNARD, HENRY, 1811-1900 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Autograph signature and address, written on back of ms fragment
      Gift of Mrs. Van Husan Moore
  - BARNITZ, PARK (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - ALS to Doxey's, New York, concerning his "The Book of Jade," n. p., undated
  - BARR, AMELIA EDITH HUDDLESTON, 1831-1919 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Autograph quotation signed
      1 leaf illus. (port.)
      Gift of James T. Babb, 1959
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Cornwall, N. Y., [1887] October 28
    - ALS to John Phillips Street, New York, N. Y., [1891]
      Concerning his request for permission to dramatize her The Bow of Orange Ribbon
    - ALS to Dr. William Hayes Ward, Cornwall on Hudson, N. Y., 1911 Febrauary 22
      Concerning a photograph of her daughter Lillie
    - Dancing and Skating. AMS
      9 numbered l.
      Leaves mounted and bound with typed transcript, 5 leaves
      Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1961 in honor of Evan Frankel
  - BARR, LOCKWOOD, 1883- (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "How Flowers got their Names..." Typewritten and carbon copies, undated
      41 page [ea.]
      Gift of Edward Ingraham, September 1941
  - BARTLETT, JOHN RUSSELL, 1805-1886 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - ALS to J. H. Woodward, Providence, R. I., 1868 January 23
  - BASCOM, JOHN, 1827-1911 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Lowell's Books." AMS, a ten-line poem [about James Russell Lowell]
  - BATCHELLER, GEORGE CLINTON (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Form letter to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1908 January 1
  - BATES, CHARLOTTE FISKE, 1838-1916 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - 1 excerpt, 4 lines of poetry, signed, from "Living by the Minute," in "Risk, and Other Poems" (1879)
  - BATES, KATHARINE LEE, 1859-1929 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - When Lincoln Died. Typescript (carbon) of poem
      2 numbered l.
      Gift of Mrs. Scoville
  - BAXTER, JAMES PHINNEY, 1831-1921 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Portland, Me., 1885 January 13
    - "Life's Looms," Autograph MS poem sent as enclosure with above letter to E. C. Stedman, Portland, Me.
      Removed from: his Idyls of the year ...1884
  - BAY, J. CHRISTIAN (JENS CHRISTIAN), 1871-1962 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Original ms poem, "Newton on Blackstone," -- two stanzas, 12 lines -- signed and dated, 1937 June 30
      Removed from: copy of A. Edward Newton's Newton on Blackstone, Philadelphia, 1937-1938
      Gift of George Watson Cole
  - BAYLOR, FRANCES COURTENAY, 1848-1920 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - ALS to W. E. Ambler, Elmwood, Va., [1888] February 17
      With original addressed envelope
      Enclosing an autograph quotation from her Behind the Blue Ridge, in response to his request for a page of manuscript
  - BAYNE, HUGH AIKEN, 1870-1954 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Mark Twain Crosses the Ocean with Sixteen Yale Boys: typewritten ms [with carbon copy]
      5 pages
      Gift of the author, August 1943
  - BEACH, REX, 1877-1949 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - With Interest To Date. TMS with autograph note at end, dated, 1909
      31 numbered l.
      Clipping and news photo included
      Gift of Carroll A. Means, October 1951
  - BEARD, DANIEL CARTER, 1850-1941, 2 (Box 3, Folder 77-78)
    - TLS to James T[inkham] Babb. Suffern, N. Y., 1934 September 1
      [Gift of Mr. Babb, 1959]
    - Notes on illustrations for Mark Twain's Connecticut Yankee, 1934 May 8
      As told to W. L. Pforzheimer, 1935 and Alexander O. Vietor, 1936 by D. C. Beard, the illustrator, as he showed them the original drawings for the book in Suffern, N. Y.
      Gift of W. L. Pforzheimer
  - BEARD, W. H. (WILLIAM HOLBROOK), 1824-1900 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - ALS to [Benjamin] H. Ticknor, Fairhaven, 1883 August 13
      Removed from: Za copy of J. C. Harris's Nights with Uncle Remus, Boston, 1883
  - BEAUX, CECILIA, 1855-1942, 2 (Box 3, Folder 80-81)
    - 5 ALS and 1 TLS to George Dudley Seymour, New York, N. Y., 1935 April-November
      Gift of Mr. Seymour, March 1943
    - Autograph
      Gift of Dr. J. H. Penniman, 1921
  - BEEBE, LUCIUS MORRIS, 1902-1966 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - 3 TLS to Andrew Keogh, New York, 1925, 1929
      Gift of Mr. Keogh
    - TLS to Wilmarth S[heldon] Lewis, New York, 1935 December 9
      Gift of W. S. Lewis
    - TLS to George Van Santvoord, "Wednesday," Cambridge, Mass., [1924]
      Gift of Mr. Van Santvoord, 1957
  - BEER, THOMAS, 1889-1940 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - 6 letters, some in his hand and some typewritten, and a telegram to Emerson Tuttle: Hartford, Nantucket, and Yonkers, undated, 1933-1934
      Laid in: 3 pages of notes in the hand of Emerson Tuttle, explaining various references in the correspondence
      Gift of Emerson Tuttle, October 1940
  - BEERS, HENRY AUGUSTIN, 1847-1926, 2 (Box 3, Folder 84-85)
    - ALS to Thomas O[llive] Mabbott [concerning publication of an article by (Nathaniel Parker) Willis], New Haven, Conn., 1919 August 4
      Presented by Prof. T. O. Mabbott of Hunter College, N. Y., February 1958
    - ALS to J[ohn] W[illiam] Weidemeyer concerning an article on Donald G. Mitchell, New Haven, Conn., 1887 September 21
      Purchased from C. S. Moeller, 1 August 1958
  - BEHRMAN, S. N. (SAMUEL NATHANIEL), 1893-1973 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Brief Moment, 3-act play. Two typescripts (carbons)
      131 leaf, 141 leaf
      Gift of the New York Public Library
  - BELASCO, DAVID, 1853-1931 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - ANS to James Gibbons Huneker, New York, N. Y., 1910 May 12
      Plain funds, September 1941
  - BELKNAP, JEREMY, 1744-1798, 2 (Box 3, Folder 88-89)
    - ALS to an unidentified correspondent, Boston, Mass., 1796 September 26
      Removed from: Aldis copy of his The Foresters (1792)
    - ALS to the Rev. Mr. [David] McClure, Boston, Mass., 1797 November 24
      Docketed by recipient on verso Gift of James T. Babb, 1959
  - BELL, LILIAN, 1867-1929 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - ALS to Mr. Downing [?], Chicago, Ill., October 8
  - BELLAMY, EDWARD, 1850-1898, 7 (Box 3, Folder 91-97)
    - A Love Story Reversed. Original ms
      53 [i.e. 57] numbered l.
      Signed at end, and with author's name and return address on leaf 1.
      As printed in the Century magazine. Reprinted in his The blindman's world and other stories (1898)
      Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, in honor of Mr. and Mrs. David Borowitz, December 1962
    - [How I Came To Write "Looking Backward"]: original MS of article printed in "The Ladies' Home Journal," April 1894. With author's signature at end of last page